<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fazi_RDA</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Fazi_RDA</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© {year} fazi_rda</copyright>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Antidepressants in the UK: Exploring Prescription Data</title>
      <link>/blog/antidep/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/antidep/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis is a simple exploratory analysis about the prescriptions of antidepressants in the UK. The data was freely obtained from the following link: https://www.kaggle.com/lsind18/prescriptions-of-antidepressants, where more information about the specifics can be found.
Notes about the dataBefore progressing further, there are a couple of points that need to be noted about the data:
1). As it is not possible to capture all information perfectly, some data can be missing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art and Machines - Experimenting with GANs</title>
      <link>/blog/dcgan/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/dcgan/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionGenerative Adversarial Networks (GANs) are one of the more advanced forms of machine learning/deep learning models present. In short, a GAN is used to analyse a given set of training data in order to synthetically produce “fake” data that is highly similar to the original sample. This is done by using two models in the framework: a generator and a discriminator. The discriminator determines whether a given piece of data is fake or real, and the generator works to generate data that is good enough to fool the discriminator, hence creating plausible (even possibly perfect) synthetic data that would actually seem to be part of the training data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Art and Machines - Neural Style Transfer</title>
      <link>/blog/neuralstyle/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/neuralstyle/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe aim of this post is to explain the overall process of neural style transfer as simply as possible, while avoiding technical jargon unless necessary. This is done so that an individual who is not well versed in machine learning and data analytic techniques is also able to appreciate and understand the unique nature of this deep learning method, and its potential implications. The technique was introduced in the paper A Neural Algorithm of Artistic Style (Gatys et.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brent Oil Prices - Time Series with ML Models</title>
      <link>/blog/brent-oil/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/brent-oil/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionWhile traditional time series models such as the Exponential Smoothing and ARIMA families are perfectly capable of making sound forecasts, there are some instances where such models are unable to fully capture what the data is portraying. In such cases, especially where the highest predictive power is required and favoured over model interpretability, advanced machine learning methods can be useful. In this analysis, the daily prices of Brent Oil(20th May 1987 - 21st April 2020) are going to be examined.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classifying Divorce</title>
      <link>/blog/divorce/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/divorce/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following analysis is a classification problem, where the goal is to try and predict divorce based on a “Divorce Predictors Scale”. The data was developed based on a psychology study named Gottman couples therapy, and was freely obtained via http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/Divorce+Predictors+data+set. The link to the original study from which this data emerged is https://dergipark.org.tr/en/pub/nevsosbilen/issue/46568/549416. The aim here is to utilise the answers by couples to 54 questions regarding their marriage to try and predict whether the marriage is intact or if divorce is imminent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Classifying Strokes - Balancing Classes with SMOTE</title>
      <link>/blog/strokes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/strokes/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following analysis is a simple classification problem, with the aim of predicting whether a patient would likely experience a stroke based on certain input factors. These factors include variables such as age, gender and other lifestyle related parameters. While the classification problem in itself is quite simple, the problem of unbalanced classes within the target variable is prominent in this dataset. In order to accommodate this imbalance, the SMOTE (Synthetic Minority Oversampling Technique) method will be described and used later.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cocaine Trees - Predicting Prices with Random Forests</title>
      <link>/blog/cocaine-prices/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/cocaine-prices/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following analysis utilises data comprising of cocaine prices available on an online hidden marketplace called Dream Market, available on the deep web. This data was freely obtained at https://www.kaggle.com/everling/cocaine-listings, with further details about the data available in the description. As the title might suggest, the goal of this analysis is attempting to accurately predict the cocaine prices based on the variables provided, utlising the Random Forests (RF) method.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Computer Prices with Simple Regression</title>
      <link>/blog/computers/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/computers/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis analysis involves a simple prediction problem. The dataset has been designed for basic data analysis, and is suitable for applying introductory predictive methods. The goal is to simply gain an understanding into the analytical process using two basic predictive models: Linear Regression and Multiple Adaptive Regression Splines (MARS).
The dataset contains some information about computers, with the dependant variable in this case being price, and other features including speed, RAM, screen etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dementia Classification - Interpreting models with LIME</title>
      <link>/blog/dementia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/dementia/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis is a fairly simple binary classification problem using data generated from MRI scans of the human brain. The data is provided by the Open Access Series of Imaging Studied (OASIS) to enable further research and discoveries in the neuroscience field. The dataset (https://www.kaggle.com/jboysen/mri-and-alzheimers) used in this specific project relates to longitudinal MRI data, with the following relevant features:
Group: patient is either demented or non-demented (Target Variable)M.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drugs and Memories - The impact of Interaction in Regressions</title>
      <link>/blog/drugs-and-memories/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/drugs-and-memories/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis is a simple analysis examining how variables interacting with each other can impact regression performance. The data set has only nine features, out of which there will be further feature selection, thereby making it easy to understand the effects. The data was freely obtained from https://www.kaggle.com/steveahn/memory-test-on-drugged-islanders-data. It describes the results of an experiment which observes the effects of anti-anxiety medicine on memory recall, while simultaneously including the effect of happy and sad memories.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epileptic Seizure Recognition with Deep Learning</title>
      <link>/blog/seizure_final/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/seizure_final/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis project attempts to classify whether a patient is suffering from an epileptic seizure or not based on certain known features. The dataset was freely obtained from the following link: https://www.kaggle.com/harunshimanto/epileptic-seizure-recognition. To summarise the data, the features comprise of individual data points of an EEG recording, monitoring a subject’s brain activity at different points in time. Further details about the specifications of these variables can be found via the given link.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finance x Data Analysis: Portfolio Optimization and Returns</title>
      <link>/blog/finance-portfolio-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/finance-portfolio-analysis/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe purpose of this project is to highlight potential applications of data analysis within the finance industry. When it comes to choosing viable securities to invest in based on a certain criteria, there are different methods that can be used, including fundamental or quantitative analysis. The focus in this project is on a quantitative approach, using the price of 10 different stocks to determine an optimum portfolio that generates required returns based on certain risks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>House Price Predictions with Clusters and Regressions</title>
      <link>/blog/house-price/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/house-price/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis analysis involves combining two modelling techniques to predict house prices: clustering and regressions. The data describes real estate valuations in the Xindian Dsitrict, New Tapei City, Taiwan, and was obtained from the following link: http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/Real+estate+valuation+data+set. While the original data file is in the xlsx format, some quick preprocessing was done in Excel (shorten variable names and convert to csv), just to make things more convenient. There are 7 variables, namely:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Jazz, Metal, Electronic - Analyzing and Clustering Music</title>
      <link>/blog/music/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/music/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionTo appreciate the flexibility of data analysis, this project aims to explore the applications of analytic techniques on audio data. The role of audio currently within data science is increasingly strengthening, with machine learning applications being used for voice sentiment analysis and developing voice assistant services as an example. In this project, music data from three highly different genres(jazz, metal and electronic) will be used for analysis. Each genre is represented by one artist, with Miles Davis for jazz, Opeth for metal, and Deadmau5 for electronic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mental Health and Suicide - Imputation with MICE, Data Dashboard</title>
      <link>/blog/mental-suicide/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/mental-suicide/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe data used in this project combines various data sources for exploratory analysis. Data related to suicide rates and mental health facilities in various countries has been sourced from here, which has further been referenced from data provided by the World Health Organization (WHO). The mental health data provided by WHO states the approximate suicide rates per 100,000 population is various countries by age and gender, while also providing figures related to the facilities and human resources available for mental health care in each country.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mining Religious and Sacred Texts</title>
      <link>/blog/religious-and-sacred-texts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/religious-and-sacred-texts/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis is an exercise in simple text mining. Five different religious and sacred texts are analysed, namely the King James Bible, the Koran, the Book of Meditations, the Gospel of Buddha and the Book of Mormon. The analysis is structured in two segments. First, the text data is processed and some visual analysis is performed, simply to gather a better understanding about these texts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mining Religious and Sacred Texts - Visualizing Clusters with UMAP</title>
      <link>/blog/umap-clust/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/umap-clust/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis analysis is a continuation of the previous post regarding religious and sacred text analysis. In the previous post, a simple exploratory analysis was performed, along with an attempt to use k-means clustering to further understand the data. However, perhaps due to the size and complexity of the data, a suitable value for k could not be found. To take a different approach to clustering, the UMAP algorithim is now going to be used instead to attempt to visualize clusters in the texts (if there are any).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OkCupid Online Dating Profiles - Visualizing the differences/similarities between men and women</title>
      <link>/blog/okcupid/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/okcupid/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionWhile online match-making and dating services/websites have tried to streamline the process of finding a romantic partner, this has also simultaneously amplified the question of what someone might be looking for in a potential match. The reason for this amplification is the significant amount of additional tangible data that has been added into the match-making equation. This data is produced when a user of these online platforms is asked to fill out details specific to themselves to make a profile describing themselves, which other people can use to judge their suitability.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Poetry Classification with KNNs</title>
      <link>/blog/poems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/poems/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following is an exercise in multi-class text classification, with the data comprising of various poems. The poems in this project are classified according to their category type: love, nature, and mythology &amp;amp; folklore. K-nearest neighbours (KNN) is the machine learning algorithm used here for classification. While there are more robust algorithms available, KNN was selected due to its advantages for being quite simple to understand and implement. It also does not require any assumptions about the data, and can therefore be used on classes that are not linearly separable as well, which is quite likely the case with text data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predicting Forest Fires with Regressions</title>
      <link>/blog/forest-fires/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/forest-fires/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following analysis aims to attempt a difficult regression task of predicting the burned area caused by forest fires. The data is based on the north-east region of Portugal, and comprises of meteorological and other data. The link to the data set is http://archive.ics.uci.edu/ml/datasets/Forest+Fires. This is based on the original work done by Cortez and Morais (2007), where the authors utilised data mining techniques to predict forest fires. A somewhat simpler approach is utlised in this analysis as compared to the original, with similarities in terms of feature engineering and error metrics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sao Paulo Temperature - Time Series with Exponential Smoothing Models</title>
      <link>/blog/sao-paulo-temperature/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/sao-paulo-temperature/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis time series analysis involves modelling the average monthly temperature in the city of Sao Paulo, Brazil. The data spans across 74 years, and was freely obtained from the following link: https://www.kaggle.com/volpatto/temperature-timeseries-for-some-brazilian-cities?select=station_sao_paulo.csv. The goal of the analysis is to utilise three exponential smoothing models (Simple Exponential Smoothing (SES), Holt Method, Holt-Winters (HW) method) and determine which of these three models performs the best for forecasting the monthly average temperature.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smoking and Visualizing - Exploring Tobacco Use and Mortality Data</title>
      <link>/blog/tobacco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/tobacco/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe data used in this visual exploratory analysis describes information related to tobacco use in England, from 2004-2015. The data was obtained from https://www.kaggle.com/nhs/tobacco-use, and contains five different data files, each describing a specific aspect. These are as follows:
Admissions =&amp;gt; Hospital admissions attributed to tobacco useFatalities =&amp;gt; Fatalities attributed to tobacco useMetrics =&amp;gt; Household expenditures on tobacco (index values)Prescriptions =&amp;gt; Prescription information attributed to tobacco useSmokers =&amp;gt; Smokers by age as percentage of populationThe aim here is to simply create clear and aesthetically appealing visualizations, which can provide sufficient insight about each of the five data files.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>US Unemployment - Time Series and Neural Networks</title>
      <link>/blog/us-unemp/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/us-unemp/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThis report differs slightly from the rest of the projects on this website. Over here, the main focus will be more on gaining an understanding of the process, as opposed to solving a specific problem. The focus here will be to simply try and understand and discuss how neural network architectures (RNN specifically) can be applied to time series data. The ultimate objective here is to appreciate the process as simply and succinctly as possible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vehicle Accidents in Canada - Exploring and Classifying Severity</title>
      <link>/blog/accidents-canada/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/accidents-canada/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following analysis is performed on data describing various vehicle accidents in Canada during the years 1999-2014. The focus is on how severe the accidents were in terms of fatalities and injuries. The link between the degree of severity and majority of the other given variables (features) is explored through visualizations. A couple of simple machine learning models are also fit to the dataset to explore whether there is any useful potential for being able to predict fatalities based on the provided features.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Visualizing Happiness - World Happiness Report 2019</title>
      <link>/blog/whr-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/whr-2019/</guid>
      <description>IntroductionThe following is a simple exercise in visualizing data. The data used is from the World Happiness Report for the year 2019, and was obtained freely from: https://www.kaggle.com/unsdsn/world-happiness?select=2019.csv. The aim is to generate some simple insights about the data using only visualizations.
Loading the data and required libraries:
#Load Librarieslibrary(tidyverse)library(reshape2)library(corrplot)#Read Data..whr19 &amp;lt;- read.csv(&amp;quot;whr-2019.csv&amp;quot;)Data processingBefore moving forward with the visuals, the data needs to be processed a little bit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>